{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The events at this location became widely known fifty years later thanks to a book by Stuart\nLake. The incident here resulted in the death of Tom and Frank McLaury as well as Billy\nClanton, though the \"law\" side suffered no casualties among Doc Holliday or Wyatt Earp. For 10\npoints, name this place in Tombstone, Arizona where an 1881 \"shootout\" took place.",
      "answer": "the O.K. Corral"
    },
    {
      "question": "The proposal to join this body was opposed in the Lodge Reservations, which specifically\nobjected to Article X (ten) of its charter, committing all members to repel any aggression against\none. William Borah's Irreconcilables movement drummed up public resistance to American\nparticipation in this organization. For 10 points, name this ineffective international body created\nby the Treaty of Versailles, which the U.S. never joined despite Woodrow Wilson's protestations.",
      "answer": "League of Nations"
    },
    {
      "question": "Following Ross Perot's most successful attempt at the Presidency, Perot embarked on a\ncampaign against this legislation, predicting it would cause a \"giant sucking sound.\" This\nlegislation was championed in a televised debate by Al Gore, and its architects included Carlos\nSalinas and Brian Mulroney. For 10 points, name this continental trade pact.",
      "answer": [
        "NAFTA",
        "North American Free Trade Agreement"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man launched the anti-hunger Operation Breadbasket as a project of his\n\"Rainbow/PUSH\" coalition. In the 1980s, he ran for the Democratic Presidential nomination\ntwice and was dogged by reports of anti-Semitism during the New York primary. For 10 points,\nname this former confidante of Martin Luther King, Jr. who became a prominent civil rights\nspokesman.",
      "answer": [
        "Jesse Jackson",
        "Jackson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When it became apparent that this event had failed, a disgusted Erich Ludendorff simply\nwalked away, leading its main organizer to be sentenced to the Landsberg, where Mein Kampf\nwas written. For 10 points, name this failed 1923 attempt by Adolf Hitler to seize power in\nGermany by leading an uprising at a Munich drinking venue.",
      "answer": "Beer Hall Putsch"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's great-grandfather raised the 1st Mississippi Partisan Rangers in the Civil War and\nwrote The White Rose of Memphis. This author used that ancestor as the model for the\nprotagonist of The Unvanquished, Colonel Sartoris. For 10 points, name this Mississippi-born\nnovelist of \"A Rose for Emily\" and The Sound and the Fury.",
      "answer": "William Faulkner, Faulkner"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man said he planned to use a Kärcher pressure-washer to \"clean out\" suburbs. In 2014,\nthis former leader of the UMP was questioned by police for alleged corruption in a judicial\nappointment in Monaco. He lost a close re-election bid in 2012 to his left-wing rival François\nHollande (pr. frah-SWAH oh-LAHND). For 10 points, name this former President of France.",
      "answer": [
        "Nicolas Sarkozy",
        "Sarkozy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Florida developer Henry Flagler got rich as a business partner of this man. Frederick Taylor\nGates advised him on how to direct his philanthropy, which included providing the startup funds\nfor Spelman College and the University of Chicago. For 10 points, name this businessman who\nwas attacked by Ida Tarbell as a monopolist after founding Standard Oil.",
      "answer": [
        "John D. Rockefeller",
        "Rockefeller",
        "John Davison Rockefeller Sr."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2014, a Senate candidate from this state was criticized for posting graphic X-rays on his\nwebsite; that second cousin of Barack Obama, Milton Wolf, failed to win the Republican\nnomination here. This state is where independent Greg Orman is seeking to unseat incumbent Pat\nRoberts. For 10 points, name this state governed by Sam Brownback from Topeka.",
      "answer": "Kansas"
    },
    {
      "question": "An early practitioner of this art form was satirized as \"elevating\" it from a hot-air balloon in\nan engraving by Honoré Daumier (pr. oh-no-RAY dow-mee-EY). This art form was used to\ndepict The Steerage by Alfred Stieglitz and Moon and Half Dome by a later American leader of\nf/64 (\"eff sixty-four\"). For 10 points, name this art form used by Ansel Adams to produce prints.",
      "answer": "photography"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"condottiere\" (pr. cahn-DOE-tee-AIR-ee) were what type of soldiers, who fought\nmost of the wars of Renaissance Italy and were often of English origin and whose use was\nwarned against by Machiavelli?",
      "answer": "mercenaries"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1850, a seeming discrepancy in this scientist’s work was resolved by Stanislao Cannizzaro.\nThis man’s breakthrough was realizing the distinction between atoms and molecules in a gas,\ncausing this veteran of the Piedmont uprising to be the namesake of the number 6.022 times 10\nto the 23rd. For 10 points, identify this discoverer of the number of particles in a mole.",
        "answer": [
          "Amadeo Avogadro",
          "Avogadro"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Avogadro was the first to correctly determine the chemical formula for what substance,\nwhich was moved against the force of gravity by Archimedes’s Screw?",
        "answer": "water"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This queen came to the throne at age six, leading to the creation of a regency council\ndominated by Axel Oxenstierna (pr. OCK-sens-TURR-nuh). In 1654, this queen shocked\nEurope by abdicating her throne and converting to Catholicism, after which she lived out her life\nin Rome. For 10 points, name this daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, an “enlightened monarch” of\nSweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Queen Christina",
          "Christina"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Christina’s energetic studies with what philosopher of Discourse on Method, whom she\nsummoned to Sweden and often woke before dawn, are thought to have caused his death?",
        "answer": "Rene Descartes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Eighth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution copied nearly verbatim this text’s prohibition\non “excessive bail and cruel and unusual punishments.” This document guaranteed freedom of\nspeech and the right to bear arms, and it also banned Catholics from succeeding to the throne.\nFor 10 points, name this 1689 law which outlined liberties prior to the Glorious Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "English Bill of Rights",
          "Bill of Rights"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What editor of The North Briton whose slogan was “No Liberty, No King” caused\nrepeated scandals in 1760s England by invoking the English Bill of Rights in his campaign\nagainst George III?",
        "answer": [
          "John Wilkes",
          "Wilkes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This god's oracle was located at Dodona. Phidias used the ivory-and-gold material\nchryselephantine to depict this god for one of the Wonders of the Ancient World. This god was\nbelieved to have survived the cannibalism of his father Cronus by being swapped with a stone.\nFor 10 points, name this thunder god and head of the Greek pantheon.",
        "answer": "Zeus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Wonder of the Ancient World was the Colossus of Rhodes, which depicted\nwhat Titan god of the sun?",
        "answer": "Helios"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was approached by Thomas Edison's agent Theo Wangemann in 1889, leading him\nto make the first-ever audio recording by a leading composer. This composer relied on Martin\nLuther's translation of the Bible as the text for his German Requiem. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer whom Hans von Bulow first grouped with Beethoven and Bach as the \"Three Bs.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Johannes Brahms",
          "Brahms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brahms was born in what city, now the second largest city by population of Germany\nand once a major center of the Hanseatic League?",
        "answer": "Hamburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician purged opponents in the \"Anti-Rightist Campaign\" after encouraging dissenters\nto identify themselves in the Hundred Flowers movement. Following news of the Secret Speech,\nthis politician led his country away from Nikita Khrushchev's Soviet Union in the late 1950s. For\n10 points, name this Long March leader and longtime \"chairman\" of Communist China.",
        "answer": [
          "Mao Zedong",
          "Mao Tse-tung"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What late 1950s program championed by Mao involved producing steel in backyard\nfurnaces in a disastrous attempt to overtake Soviet and American industrial capacity?",
        "answer": "Great Leap Forward"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This theory was advocated by John Needham due to a faulty experimental design. Lazzaro\nSpallanzani argued against this theory by showing that Needham had failed to entirely seal the\nboiled flask used before observing “animalcules.” For 10 points, name this theory finally put to\nrest by Louis Pasteur, which holds that rotting food directly creates life.",
        "answer": "spontaneous generation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What scientist, the namesake of cells found around nerves, coined the dogma that “all\ncells come from pre-existing cells” following the collapse of spontaneous generation theory?",
        "answer": [
          "Theodor Schwann",
          "Schwann"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1905, Germany's Kaiser Wilhelm II landed at this country's port of Tangier to support its\nindependence, causing a crisis with France. This country is also home to the headgear namesake\nFez and to the site of a January 1943 Allied summit that first formulated the \"unconditional\nsurrender\" doctrine. For 10 points, name this country which hosted the Casablanca Conference.",
        "answer": "Morocco"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The next Allied conference was held in what city, which was planned by Pierre\nL'Enfant and burned down after the Battle of Bladensburg in 1814?",
        "answer": [
          "Washington D.C.",
          "District of Columbia",
          "Washington"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE SOUTH SEA BUBBLE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "England's South Sea Bubble scandal of 1720...\nArose over a company which transported what kind of people in the \"Middle Passage\" after\nforcible abduction from Africa?",
          "answer": [
            "slaves",
            "slave"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the creation of what office, later held by Margaret Thatcher and David Cameron?",
          "answer": [
            "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom",
            "Prime Minister",
            "First Lord of the Treasury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Occurred during the reign of what first Hanoverian king?",
          "answer": "George I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the ascension of what party, which opposed the Tories in the eighteenth-century British\nparty system?",
          "answer": [
            "Whigs",
            "Whig"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Temporarily soured the English investor class on what form of business entity which preceded\ncorporations and was prominent during the Age of Exploration?",
          "answer": "joint-stock company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arose from an attempt to exploit the Treaty of Utrecht, which ended what war in 1713?",
          "answer": [
            "War of the Spanish Succession",
            "Spanish Succession"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was resolved by what politician who dominated the British government until 1742?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Walpole",
            "Walpole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Caused the creation of what institution, which manages UK monetary policy?",
          "answer": "Bank of England"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POST-WAR ITALY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "In Italy after World War II, who or what was the...\nIdeology advocated by the Red Brigades terrorist group and Italy's neighbor Yugoslavia?",
          "answer": [
            "Communism",
            "Marxism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized crime phenomenon which was curtailed in the \"Maxi trial?\"",
          "answer": "the mafia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization formed by the Maastricht Treaty which Italy was an architect of?",
          "answer": [
            "European Union",
            "EU"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Western military alliance which orchestrated Operation Gladio in Italy?",
          "answer": [
            "NATO",
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Media mogul who became Italy's right-wing prime minister three times and was frequently\ncharged with corruption?",
          "answer": [
            "Silvio Berlusconi",
            "Berlusconi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Milan-based designer who founded what is now Italy's largest men's fashion house in 1975?",
          "answer": [
            "Giorgio Armani",
            "Armani"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Umbrella auto manufacturer which now owns Ferrari, Maserati, and Chrysler?",
          "answer": "Fiat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name commonly given to the period of political violence from 1969 to the mid-1980s?",
          "answer": [
            "Years of Lead",
            "Anni di piombo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MILLARD FILLMORE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. President Millard Fillmore…\nWas the last President to belong to neither of what two parties?",
          "answer": [
            "Democrats and Republicans",
            "Democrat and Republican"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded what “Old Rough and Ready” Mexican War hero, who died in office?",
          "answer": [
            "Zachary Taylor",
            "Taylor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first President inaugurated after the dedication of what 555-foot obelisk in D.C.?",
          "answer": "Washington Monument"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent what \"Commodore\" to open trade with Japan?",
          "answer": [
            "Matthew Perry",
            "M Perry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Recognized Utah as a territory under the leadership of what Mormon church president?",
          "answer": [
            "Brigham Young",
            "Young"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed what omnibus bill which sought to resolve free-slave state concerns?",
          "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted to regain the Presidency in 1856 under the banner of what third party?",
          "answer": [
            "Know-Nothing Party",
            "Know-Nothing",
            "American Party",
            "American"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Approved the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty, which concerned the future construction of what route?",
          "answer": "Panama Canal"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This body was originally under the influence of John Pym and the radical \"Five\nMembers,\" and it was convened to raise money following the Bishops' Wars. This body\nsteadily lost members, ending up named sardonically for Nicholas (20 pts) ",
        "Barebones, after its\nmoderate delegates were removed in Pride's Purge to create the (10 pts) ",
        "Rump Parliament. For 10\npoints, name this Parliament which oversaw the English Civil War and is named because it sat\nfrom 1640 to 1660."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Long Parliament",
        "Long"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man expanded his Keystone Bridge Company into his business empire, which\ngreatly profited from introducing the Bessemer process to widespread use in America. This\nman's 1899 article \"The (20 pts) ",
        "Gospel of Wealth\" outlined his philanthropic plans, which\nincluded founding several (10 pts) ",
        "library systems now named for him. For 10 points, name this\nScottish immigrant who became the greatest steel magnate of the late nineteenth century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Andrew Carnegie",
        "Carnegie"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexey Leonov posits that the training crash which killed this man in 1968 was caused by\nan accidental near-miss with another fighter jet. This man, who was selected out of twenty\ncandidates from (20 pts) ",
        "Star City, whistled the patriotic song \"The Motherland Hears\" while\nre-entering the atmosphere aboard (10 pts) ",
        "Vostok 1. For 10 points, name this Soviet cosmonaut\nwho, in 1961, became the first human to leave the Earth's atmosphere."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yuri Gagarin",
        "Gagarin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 2001 panel of experts in this sport named Regla Torres and Lorenzo Bernardi among\nits three best players of all time. William Morgan invented this game in 1895 as a less\nphysical use of (20 pts) ",
        "basketball courts. Al Scates is the most successful coach in this sport,\nand was the trainer of the generally regarded best-ever player at this sport, (10 pts) ",
        "Karch\nKiraly. For 10 points, name this game in which a libero, blockers, and setters play across an\nelevated net."
      ],
      "answer": "volleyball"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Brooks Henderson was the initial special prosecutor in charge of resolving this\nscandal, but was replaced with James Broadhead after appearing too incorruptible. This\nscandal was organized in St. Louis and involved personal (20 pts) ",
        "secretary Orville Babcock.\nTreasury secretary Benjamin (10 pts) ",
        "Bristow exposed this affair in 1875. For 10 points, name this\nscandal involving the embezzlement of tax revenues on liquor which came to discredit the Grant\nadministration."
      ],
      "answer": "Whiskey Ring"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A road extending from Castrum Truentinum to the Aurelian Walls of Rome was named\nfor this substance, whose transportation was the impetus for building some of the oldest\nknown (20 pts) ",
        "roads. This substance was traded to the north in exchange for gold from the (10 pts) ",
        "African interior, especially by the Ghana empire. For 10 points, identify this formerly valuable\nsubstance which can now be easily retrieved from natural sources such as seawater and is often\niodized."
      ],
      "answer": "salt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man successfully completed the \"red line\" map as part of the plan for a \"Cape to\nCairo railway.\" This man was sent as the agent of the Rothschild company to (20 pts) ",
        "Kimberley, where he spent seventeen years buying competing diamond fields. He founded\nthe (10 pts) ",
        "De Beers company to cement his monopoly over the industry. For 10 points, name this\nBritish colonialist in South Africa who endowed a series of scholarships for foreign students at\nOxford."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cecil Rhodes",
        "Rhodes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Guns fired from this building ended the Battle of the Faubourg St. Antoine (pr. foo-BOO\nsont AHN-twan) during the Fronde. This building is where the Marquis de (20 pts) ",
        "Sade enraged\ncrowds by claiming a plot to massacre its inhabitants. Only seven politically unimportant (10 pts) ",
        "prisoners were found inside when it was stormed on July 14, 1789. For 10 points, name this\nParis prison which was destroyed to start the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "the Bastille"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) In 1595, the Tooth of the Buddha was moved to a reliquary on this island, where the\nKingdom of Kandy long held out against colonization. In the twentieth century, this island\nhad the world's first (20 pts) ",
        "female prime minister, and its (10 pts) ",
        "Sinhalese majority fought a\nprotracted war with a terrorist group that invented suicide bombing. For 10 points, name this\nisland country where the Tamil Tigers fought against the government at Colombo, often spilling\ninto nearby India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "Lanka"
      ]
    }
  ]
}
